<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<body>
    <title>Šahrestānīhā ī Ērān šahr</title>


    <title>
        <seg xml:id="tp_1" xml:lang="pal" corresp="te_1">[šahr<interp>estān</interp>īhā ī ērān]</seg>
        <seg xml:id="te_1" xml:lang="en" corresp="tp_1">The Provincial Capitals of Ērān-šahr</seg>
    </title>

    <head>
        <seg xml:id="hp_1" xml:lang="pal" corresp="he_1">pad nām ī dādār ī weh abzōnīg</seg>
        <seg xml:id="he_1" xml:lang="en" corresp="hp_1">In the name of the beneficient bountiful Creator</seg></head> 
        
    <head>
        <seg xml:id="hp_2" xml:lang="pal" corresp="he_2">pad nām ud nērōg ud ayārīh ī dādār Ohrmazd ǰadag ī nēk.</seg>
        <seg xml:id="he_2" xml:lang="en" corresp="hp_2">In the name and power and righteousness of the Creator Ohrmazd and good omen.</seg>
    </head>

    <text>
        
        <s n="1">
            <seg xml:id="p_1" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_1"> šahr<interp>est</interp>ānīhā ī andar zamīg ī Ērān šahr kerd estēd ǰud ǰud būm kū kadām sar-xwadāy kerd pad gōkān abar ēn ayādgār nibišt estēd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_1" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_1">The cities in the land of Ērān-šahr which have been built in different days, where and which overlord made them is written in detail in this memoir.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="2">
            <seg xml:id="p_2" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_2">pad kust ī xwarāsān samarkand šahrestān kay-us ī kawādān bun fragand siyāwaxš ī kay-usān bē frazāmēnīd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_2" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_2">In the Eastern direction, the foundation of the city of Samarkand was laid by Kāus, the son of Kawād. Sīyāwaxš, the son of Kāus completed it.</seg> </s>
        
        <s n="3">
            <seg xml:id="p_3" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_3">kay-husrō ī siyāwaxšān ānōh zād u-š warzāwand ātaxš wahrām ānōh nišāst.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_3" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_3">Kay Husraw, the son of Sīyāwaxš was born there, and he set the miraculous Wahrām fire there.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="4">
            <seg xml:id="p_4" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_4">pas Zardušt dēn āwurd az framān <interp>ī</interp> wištāsp-šā hazār ud dō-sad fragard pad dēn-dibīrīh pad taxtagīhā <interp>ī</interp> zarrēn kand ud nibišt ud pad ganǰ<interp>ī</interp> ān ātaxš nihād.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_4" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_4">Then Zoroaster brought the Religion. By the order of king Wištāsp 1200 fragard (chapters) in the script of religious scripture were engraved on golden tablets and written and deposited in the treasury of that fire-(temple).</seg></s>
        
        <s n="5">
            <seg xml:id="p_5" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_5">ud pas gizistag skandar sōxt ud andar ō drayāb abgand.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_5" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_5">And then the accursed Alexander burnt and threw it into the sea.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="6">
            <seg xml:id="p_6" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_6">sugd ī haft āšyān u-š haft āšyānīh ēd kū haft āšyān andar būd: ēk ān ī J̌am ud ēk <interp>ān</interp> ī azdahāg ud ēk ān<interp>ī</interp> Frēdōn ud ēk ān ī manūčihr ud ēk ān ī kay-us ud ēk ān ī kay-husrō ud ēk ān ī luhrāsp ud ēk ān ī wištāsp-šā.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_6" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_6">Sogdiana (has) seven abodes, its having seven abodes in it means that there were seven Lords in it. One belonging to Jam and one to Aži Dahāg and one to Frēdōn and one to Manūčihr and one to Kāus and one to Lohrāsp and one to king Wištāsp.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="7">
            <seg xml:id="p_7" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_7">pas gizistag frāsiyāg ī tūr harw ēk nišēmag ī šāhān uzdes-zār-ēw bašn padiš kdrd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_7" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_7">Then the accursed Frāsiyāk, the Tūrānian, made seats for each of the demons, and an idol temple and a heathen temple.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="8">
            <seg xml:id="p_8" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_8">andar baxl ī bāmīg šahrestān<interp>ī</interp> nawāzag spandyād ī wištāspān kerd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_8" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_8">In the brilliant Balx, the city of Nawāzag was built by Spandyād, the son of Wištāsp.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="9">
            <seg xml:id="p_9" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_9">u-š warzāwand ātaxš wahrām ānōh nišāst u-š nēzag ī xwēš ānōh bē zad u-š ō yabbū-xāgān ud sinǰēbīk-xāgān ud čōl xāgān ud wazurg-xān ud gōhram ud tuzāb ud arzāsp ī xyōnān-šā paygām frēstīd kū nēzag ī man bē nigerēd harw kē pad wēzišn ī ēn nēzag nigerēd čē andar ō Ērān šahr dwārēd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_9" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_9">And he set the miraculous Wahrām fire there and struck his lance there and he sent a message to Yabbu Xāgān, Sinjēbik Xāgān, and Čōl Xāgān and the Great Xāgān and Gohram and Tuzāb and Arzāsp, the king of the Hayōns: “behold my lance, whoever beholds the movement of this lance is like they have rushed to Iran.”</seg></s>
        
        <s n="10">
            <seg xml:id="p_10" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_10">šahrestān ī xwārazm narsēh ī yahūdagān kerd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_10" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_10">The city of Xwārazm was built by Narsēh, the son of the Jewess.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="11">
            <seg xml:id="p_11" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_11">šahrestān ī marw-rōd wahrām ī yazdagirdān kerd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_11" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_11">The city of Marv-rōd was built by Wahrām, the son of Yazdgerd.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="12">
            <seg xml:id="p_12" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_12">šahrestān ī marw ud sahrestān<interp>ī</interp> harē gizistag skandar ī harōmīg kerd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_12" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_12">The city of Marv and the city of Herāt were built by the accursed Alexander the Roman.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="13">
            <seg xml:id="p_13" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_13">šahrestān<interp>ī</interp> pōšang šāpuhr ī ardašīrān kerd u-š pad posang puhl-ē-wazurg kerd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_13" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_13">The city of Pōšang was built by Šābuhr the son of Ardaxšīr, and he built a large bridge in Pōšang.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="14">
            <seg xml:id="p_14" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_14">šahrestān<interp>ī</interp> tūs tūs ī nōdarān [kerd ī] nōh-sad sāl spāhbed būd. pas az tūs spāhbedīh ō zarēr ud az zarēr ō bastwar ud az bastwar ō karazm mad.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_14" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_14">The city of Tūs was built by Tūs, the son of Nōdar, and (he) was the general for 900 years. After Tūs, the office of general came to Zarēr and from Zarēr to Bastūr and from Bastūr to Karzam.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="15">
            <seg xml:id="p_15" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_15">šahrestān ī nēw-šāpuhr šāpuhr ī ardašīrān kerd pad ān gāh ka-š pāhlēzag <interp>ī</interp> tūr ōzad u-š pad ham gyāg šahrestān<interp>-ē</interp> framūd kerdan.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_15" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_15">The city of Nēwšābuhr was built by Šābuhr the son of Ardaxšīr. At that time when he killed the Tūrānian Pahlīzag, he ordered to build the city in the same place.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="16">
            <seg xml:id="p_16" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_16">šahrestān ī kāyēn kay-luhrāsp ī wištāsp pid kerd .</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_16" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_16">The city of Qāyēn was built by Kay Lohrāsp, the father of Wištāsp.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="17">
            <seg xml:id="p_17" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_17">andar gurgān šahrestān ī dahestān xwānēnd narsēh ī aškānān kerd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_17" xml:lang="en" corresp="p-17">In Gurgān, the city which they call Dahestān was built by Narseh, the Arsacid.</seg></s>

        <s n="18">
            <seg xml:id="p_18" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_18">šahrestān <interp>ī</interp> kūmis<interp>ud</interp> panǰ burg azdahāg pad šabestān kerd mānišn<interp>ī</interp> pārsīgān ānōh būd pad xwadāyīh yazdgird ī šāpuhrān kerd andar tāzišn ī čōl nērōg<interp>-ē</interp> pāhr ān ālag.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_18" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_18">The city of Kūmis of five towers Aži Dahāg made it his own harem. The abode of the *Parthians was there. In the reign of Yazdgird, the son of Šābuhr made it during the invasion of the Čōl, at the boundary of the Gruznian Guard.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="19">
            <seg xml:id="p_19" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_19">šahrestān <interp>ī</interp> panǰ-husrō:šād-husrō must-ābād-<interp>husrō</interp> ud wisp-šād-husrō ud hu-bōy-husrō šād-farrox-husrō kawādān kay-husrō kerd <interp>ud</interp> nām nihād.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_19" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_19">Five cities were built by Husraw, the son of Kawād: Husraw-šād, and Husraw ī Mūst-Ābād, and Wisp-šād-Husraw and Hū-bōy-Husraw, and Šād-farrox-Husraw and named them.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="20">
            <seg xml:id="p_20" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_20">u-š frasp-ēw kē ē sad ud haštād frasang drahnāy ud wīst <interp>ud</interp> panǰ šāh-ārešn bālā ē sad ud haštād dar kōšk<interp>ud</interp> dastgird andar framūd kerdan.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_20" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_20">He ordered the establishment of a wall 180 farsang(s) long and 25 royal cubit(s) high, 180 palace gates and ordered in it the establishment of an estate.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="21">
            <seg xml:id="p_21" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_21">pad kust<interp>ī</interp> xwarwarān šahrestān ī tīsifōn az framān ī tūs warāzag ī gēwagān kerd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="" xml:lang="" corresp="">In the Western direction, the city of Ctesiphon was built by the order of Tūs, the son of Warāz from the family of Gēw.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="22">
            <seg xml:id="p_22" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_22">šahrestān <interp>ī</interp> nasībīn warāzag<interp>ī</interp> gēwagān kerd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_22" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_22">The city of Nisibis was built by Warāzag the son of Gēw.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="23">
            <seg xml:id="p_23" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_23">šahrestān ī ōrhāy narsēh ī aškānān kerd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_23" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_23">The city of Edessa was built by Narseh, the Arsacid.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="24">
            <seg xml:id="p_24" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_24">šahrestān ī bābēl pad xwadāyīh<interp>ī</interp> J̌am kerd u-š tīr abāxtar ānōh bē bast pad mārīg<interp>ī</interp> haft <interp>ud</interp> dwāzdah axtarān ud abāxtarān ud haštom bārag pad ǰādūgīh ō mihr azērīg bē nimūd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_24" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_24">The city of Babylon was built by Bābēl during the reign of Jam. And he bound the planet Mercury there and he showed the seven planets and the twelve constellations and the eighth portions by sorcery to the Sun and to those below (mankind).</seg></s>
        
        <s n="25">
            <seg xml:id="p_25" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_25">šahrestān ī hērat šāpuhr ī ardašīrān kerd u-š mihr-zād ī hērat marz-bān pad war ī tāzīgān bē gumārd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_25" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_25">The city of Hīra was built by Šābuhr, the son of Ardaxšīr and he appointed Mihrzād the margrave of Hīra over the wall of the Arabs.</seg></s>

        <s n="26">
            <seg xml:id="p_26" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_26">šahrestān ī hamadān yazdgird ī šāpuhrān kerd kē-šān yazdgird ī dabar xwānēnd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_26" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_26">The city of Hamadān was built by Yazdgird, the son of Šābuhr whom they call Yazdgird the rough.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="27">
            <seg xml:id="p_27" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_27">andar māh ud kust ī nihāwand ud war<interp>ī</interp> wahrām-āwand šahrestān-ēw wahrām ī yazdgirdān kerd kē-šān wahrām gōr xwānd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_27" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_27">In Media and the district of Nihāwand and the fortress of Wahrāmāwand, Wahrām the son of Yazdgird whom they call Wahrām Gōr, built a city.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="28">
            <seg xml:id="p_28" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_28">wīst-ēw šahrestān ī andar padišxwārgar kerd estēd čē ēg-iš az framān ī armāyīl awēšān kōfyārān kerd kē-šān az azdahāg kōf pad šahryārīh windād estād.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_28" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_28">21 cities were built in Padišxwārgar, either Armāyīl or by the order of Armāyīl were built by the mountaineers, who from Aži Dahāg acquired the dominion of the mountains.</seg></s>

        <s n="29">
            <seg xml:id="p_29" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_29">kōfyār haft hēnd <interp>pad</interp> dumbāwand: wisēmagān ud āhagān ud wispūr ud sōbārān ud musragān ud barōzān ud marinzān.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_29" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_29"></seg></s>
        
        <s n="30">
            <seg xml:id="p_30" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_30">ēn ān būd kē-šān az azdahāg kōf pad šahryārīh windād estād.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_30" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_30">These were those who from Aži Dahāg acquired the dominion of the mountains.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="31">
            <seg xml:id="p_31" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_31">šahrestān mūsel pērōz šāpuhrān kerd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_31" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_31">The city of Mosul was built by Pērōz, the son of Šābuhr.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="32">
            <seg xml:id="p_32" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_32">nōh šahrestān andar zamīg gazīrag kerd estēd āmitūs kēsar brādar-zād kerd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_32" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_32">9 cities were built in the land of Jazīra, and Āmtūs, the nephew of Caesar built them.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="33">
            <seg xml:id="p_33" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_33">wīst čahār šahrestān andar zamīg šām<interp>ud</interp> frīgā ud kufah ud makkah ud madīnag gāh kerd estēd ast šāhān šāh ast kēsar.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_33" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_33">The 24 cities which were built in the land of Syria and Yemen and Africa and Kufa and Mecca and Medina, some were built by the King of Kings and (some built) by the Caesar.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="34">
            <seg xml:id="p_34" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_34">pad kust nēmrōz šahrestān ī kābul ardašīr ī spandyādān kerd estēd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_34" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_34">In the Southern direction, the city of Kābul was built by Ardaxšīr, the son of Spandyād.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="35">
            <seg xml:id="p_35" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_35">šahrestān raxwat rahām ī gōdarzān kerd pad ān gāh ka-š asp warz-bar ī tūr ōzad u-š yabbū-xāgān az ānōh stō bē kerd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_35" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_35">The city of Raxvat was built by Rahām, the son of Gōdarz, at that time when he, Aspwarz killed the manly Tūr, and harassed Yabbū the Xāgān from there.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="36">
            <seg xml:id="p_36" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_36">šahrestān ī bost bastwar <interp>ī</interp> zarērān kerd pad ān gāh ka wištasp-šā dēn yaštan pad frazdān būd ud bunag ī wištāsp ud abārīg wāspuhragān andar nišāst.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_36" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_36">The city of Bust was built by Bastūr, the son of Zarēr, at that time when king Wištāsp worshipped the religion by the Frazdān (lake), and the abode of Wištāsp and other blood princes was established.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="37">
            <seg xml:id="p_37" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_37">šahrestān ī frāh ud šahrestān zāwalestān rōdstahm ī sīstān-šā kerd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_37" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_37">The city of Frāh and the city of Zābul were built by Rustam, the king of Sīstān.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="38">
            <seg xml:id="p_38" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_38">šahrestān zarang naxust gizistag frāsiyāg ī tūr kerd u-š warzāwand ātaxš karkōy ānōh nišāst u-š manuščihr andar ō padišxwārgar kerd u-š Spandarmad pad zanīh
        xwāst ud Spandarmad andar ō zamīg gumēxt šahrestān awērān kerd u-š ātaxš afsārd ud pas kay-hu-sraw siyāwašān šahrestān abāz kerd u-š ātaxš karkōy abāz nišāt ud ardašīr bābagān šahrestān bun pad frazāmēnīd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_38" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_38">The city of Zarang was first built by the accursed Frāsiyāk, the Tūrānian, and established the miraculous Karkōy Fire there, and Manūčihr was (surrounded) in Padišxwargar, and (Frāsiyāk) asked Spandarmad as wife and Spandarmad mixed in the earth, (he) destroyed the city and he extinguished the fire, and then Kay Husraw, the son of Sīyāwaxš again built the city. And he again founded the Karkōy Fire, and Ardaxšīr, the son of Pābag finished the city.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="39">
            <seg xml:id="p_39" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_39">šahrestān
                kirmān pērōzān kirmān-šā kerd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_39" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_39">The city of Kermān was built by (*Kawād) the son of Pērōz, the king of Kermān.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="40">
            <seg xml:id="p_40" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_40">šahrestān weh-ardašīr pad sē xwadāy kerd ud ardašīr bābagān pad frazāmēnīd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_40" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_40">The city of Weh-Ardaxšīr was built by three lords and Ardaxšīr, the son of Pābag finished it.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="41">
            <seg xml:id="p_41" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_41">šahrestān staxr ardawān ī pārsīgān-šā kerd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_41" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_41">The city of Staxr was built by Ardawān, king of the *Parthians.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="42">
            <seg xml:id="p_42" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_42">šahrestān dārāb-kird dārāy ī dārāyān kerd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_42" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_42">The city of Dārābjird was built by Dārā, the son of Dārā.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="43">
            <seg xml:id="p_43" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_43">šahrestān weh-šāpuhr šāpuhr ī ardāšīrān kerd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_43" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_43">The city of Bēšābuhr was built by Šābuhr, the son of Ardaxšīr.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="44">
            <seg xml:id="p_44" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_44">šahrestān gōr-ardasīr-xwarrah ardāšīr bābagān kerd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_44" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_44">The city of Gōr-Ardaxšīr-Xwarrah was built by Ardaxšīr, the son of Pābag.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="45">
            <seg xml:id="p_45" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_45">šahrestān tawwag humāy ī čihr-āzādān kerd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_45" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_45">The city of Tūz was built by Humāy, the son of Čihr Āzād.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="46">
            <seg xml:id="p_46" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_46">šahrestān ī Ohrmazd ardašīrān<interp>ud</interp> šahrestān ī rām-Ohrmazd Ohrmazd nēw šāphrān kerd.</seg>
            <seg
                xml:id="e_46" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_46">The city of Hormizd-Ardaxšīr and the city of Rām-Hormizd were built by Hormizd, the valiant, the son of Šābuhr.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="47">
            <seg xml:id="p_47" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_47">šahrestān šūs ud šūstar šīšīnduxt zan ī yazdgird šāpuhrān kerd čiyōn duxt ī rēš-galūdag yahūdagān-šā mād-iz ī wahrām ī gōr būd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_47" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_47">The city of Susa and Šūštar were built by Šīšinduxṭ, the wife of Yazdgird, the son of Šābuhr, since she was the daughter of Reš Galut, the king of the Jews and also was the mother of Wahrām Gōr.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="48">
            <seg xml:id="p_48" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_48">šahrestān ī wandōy-šāpuhr ud šahrestān ī ērān-kerd-šāpuhr šapuhr ī ardašīrān kerd. u-š palābād nām nihād.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_48" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_48">The city of Wandōy-Šābuhr and the city of Ērān-kard-Šābuhr, Šābuhr, the son of Ardaxšīr built, and he named it Pīlābad.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="49">
            <seg xml:id="p_49" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_49">šahrestān ī nahr-tīrag pad duš-xwadāyīh ī azdahāg pad šabestān kerd ud zēndān ī Ērān šahr būd zēndān aškān nām būd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_49" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_49">The city of Nahr-Tīrag was built during the evil reign of Aži Dahāg as a harem, and was the prison of Ērān-šahr, and it was called the prison of the Arsac.</seg></s>

        <s n="50">
            <seg xml:id="p_50" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_50">šahrestān simrān Frēdōn ī ādwēnān kerd u-š maswar. simrān-šā ōzad u-š zamīg ī simrān abāz xwēsīh Ērān šahr āwurd u-š dašt tāzīg pad xwēsīh ud ābādīh bē ō baxt-hu-sraw ī tāzīg-šā dād paywand dārišn ī xwēš ray.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_50" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_50">The city of Himyār was built by Frēdōn, the son of Ādwēn. And he killed Masrugh, the king of Himyār, and he again brought the land of Himyār under the sovereignty of Ērān-šahr. And he gave the plain of the Arabs to Baxt Husraw, the king of the Arabs as his very own feud, on the account of the connection which he himself made with him.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="51">
            <seg xml:id="p_51" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_51">šhrestān ī ārēst šāpuhr ī ardašīrān kerd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_51" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_51">The city of Ārhēst was built by Šābuhr, the son of Ardaxšīr.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="52">
            <seg xml:id="p_52" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_52">šahrestān ī asūr ud šahrestān ī weh-ardašīr [ardašīr] ī spandyādān kerd. u-š ōšag ī hagar marzbān gund-gar ud burg-gar pad war ī tāzīgān bē gumārd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_52" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_52">The city of Āsūr and the city of Weh-Ardaxšīr were built by Ardaxšīr, the son of Spandyād. And he appointed Ōšag, of Hagar as the margrave (over the) Dō-sar and Bor-gil by the wall of the Arabs.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="53">
            <seg xml:id="p_53" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_53">šahrestān ī gay gizistag aleksandar ī flīpān kerd mānīšn ī yahūdān ānōh būd <interp>ī</interp> pad xwadāyīh <interp>ī</interp> yazdgird ī šāpuhrān nīd az xwāhišn ī šīšīnduxt ī-š zan būd .</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_53" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_53">The city of Gay was built by the accursed Alexander, the son of Philip. The dwelling of the Jews was there. During the reign of Yazdgird, the son of Šābuhr, (the Jews) were led there by the request of Šīšinduxṭ who was his wife.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="54">
            <seg xml:id="p_54" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_54">šahrestān ī ērān-āsān-kerd-kawād <interp>kawād</interp> pērōzan kerd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_54" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_54">The city of Ērān-āsān-kard-Kawād was built by (*Kawād), the son of Pērōz.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="55">
            <seg xml:id="p_55" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_55">šahrestān ī aškar wahrām ī yazdgirdān kerd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_55" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_55">The city of Aškar was built by Wahrām, the son of Yazdgird.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="56">
            <seg xml:id="p_56" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_56">šahrestān ī ādurbādagān ērān-gušnasp ī ādurbādagān spāhbed [kerd].</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_56" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_56">The city of Ādurbādagān was (built) by Ērān-Gušasp who was the general of Ādurbādagān.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="57">
            <seg xml:id="p_57" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_57">šahrestān ī wan wan ī gulaxšān kerd ud pad zanīh ō kay-kawād mad  ud drubuštīh arwand-asp <interp>ī</interp> tūr ī brād-rōš ī karb pad ǰādūgīh kerd pānagīh ī gyān xwēš rāy.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_57" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_57">The city of Wan was built by Wan, the daughter of Gulaxšān and became married to Kay Kawād, and the fortification of Arwandāsp was built by Tūr, the son Brātrēš the Karp by sorcery as a place of protection for his own life.</seg></s> 
        
        <s n="58">
            <seg xml:id="p_58" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_58">pad kust ādurbādagān šahrestān ī ganzag frāsiyāg tūr kerd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_58" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_58">In the direction of Ādurbādagān, the City of Ganzag was built by Frāsiyāk, the son of Tūr.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="59">
            <seg xml:id="p_59" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_59">šahrestān ī āmōγ zandīg ī purr-marg kerd. Zardušt ī Spitāmān az ān šahrestān būd.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_59" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_59">The city of Āmol was built by the heretic who is full of death. Zoroaster, the son of Spitāmān was from that city.</seg></s>
        
        <s n="60">
            <seg xml:id="p_60" xml:lang="pal" corresp="e_60">šahrestān ī bagdād abū-gāfar čiyōn-šān abū-dawānīg xwānd kerd. pad pērōzīh āwišt. frazaft pad drōd šādīh rāmišn.</seg>
            <seg xml:id="e_60" xml:lang="en" corresp="p_60">The city of Baghdad was built by Abū Jaʿfar whom they call Abū Dawāniq.</seg></s>
        
    </text>
</body>
